Jonathan A. DeCastro

CONTACT INFORMATION

1261 Warren Rd. Apt. A Ithaca, NY 14850

github: github.com/jadecastro

t: +1-585-425-7184 e: jad455@cornell.edu

w: jadecastro.github.io

SUMMARY OF **QUALIFICATIONS** I am a Ph.D. Candidate in Robotics with 8 years of prior industry experience and a proven ability to communicate to a variety of technical and non-technical audiences. I develop algorithms in C++, Python, and MATLAB for high-level control of robots featuring complex, nonlinear dynamics, and design and test robotic demonstrators for physical experimentation.

EDUCATION

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

Ph.D., Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering

2015-Present

Advisor: Prof. Hadas Kress-Gazit

Graduate Minors: Computer Science, Computational Science and Engineering

M.S., Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering

2011-2014

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA M.S., Mechanical Engineering

2001-2003

B.S. (with Honors), Mechanical Engineering

1996-2001

RELEVANT COURSES

Applied Math and Optimization: Linear Systems, Probability, Mathematical Programming, Convex Optimization, Heuristic Methods for Optimization

Controls and Systems: Hybrid Systems, Robust Control, Stochastic Control, Multivariable Control

Robotics and Dynamics: Intermediate Dynamics, Robot Learning, Autonomous Mobile Robots, Robotic Ma-

nipulation

HARDWARE AND SOFTWARE SKILLS Linux, Windows

C, C++, Python, Robot Operating System (ROS), MATLAB/Simulink, Microsoft Visual Studio, gcc, LaTeX,

INDUSTRY AND RESEARCH **EXPERIENCE**

Graduate Research Assistant, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

August 2011–Present

Verifiable Robotics Research Group

- Developed algorithms in C++, Python and MATLAB for automated, correct-by-construction synthesis of controllers for robots with nonlinear dynamics through application of formal methods and optimization
- Developed a novel approach to automatically synthesize revisions to robot mission specifications that cannot be realized and explain these revisions to the user via auto-generated feedback
- Authored 7 publications featured in international conference proceedings, workshops and robotics journals

Lead Engineer, Impact Technologies, LLC., Rochester, NY

July 2008-August 2011

Control and Prediction Group

- Conducted independent research on control algorithms and simulation tools for flight control and diagnostic systems and submarine navigation
- Awarded four Phase 1 and two Phase 2 Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grants as PI totaling \$1.8M for DoD- and NASA-sponsored research
- Composed technical reports and conference papers, presented to customers and stakeholders, and mentored co-op students

Research Scientist, NASA Glenn Research Center, Cleveland, OH

July 2003-July 2008

Intelligent Control and Autonomy Branch

- Designed and coded Commercial Modular Aero-Propulsion System Simulation (C-MAPSS), a MATLABbased "virtual" aircraft engine serving to extend accessibility of such models to a wide arena of researchers
- Investigated control algorithms for in-flight aircraft control reconfiguration during emergencies
- Implemented and tested various control techniques in scaled engine component test rigs

LEADERSHIP AND COMMUNICATION EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, Autonomous Mobile Robots, Cornell University

Spring 2015

• Taught lab sessions, delivered occasional lectures, graded code and reports (36 students)

Mentor, Undergraduate Research, Cornell University

Spring 2015

- Mentored seven undergraduates for two entries in the 2015 Soft Robotics Design Competition
- Earned First Prize (out of 82 teams) and Honorable Mention for outstanding project idea

Workshop Organizer, "Command Your Own Robot"

2014, 2015

- Organized and lead a hands-on robotics workshop as part of the **Expanding Your Horizons (EYH)** conference for middle-school girls interested in math and science
- Supervised a team of four to lead the activities and introduce students to opportunities for further education and careers in STEM fields

Voting Member, Cornell Graduate and Professional Student Assembly

2013-2014

• Organized several events for facilitating discussion of issues of interest (e.g. student life, compensation), between graduate students and university administration

Instructor, System Modeling, Rochester Institute of Technology

Winter 2010-2011

• Administered, lectured and graded a senior- and graduate-level course

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- **J. A. DeCastro** and H. Kress-Gazit. Synthesis of nonlinear continuous controllers for verifiably-correct high-level, reactive behaviors. *International Journal of Robotics Research*, 34(3):378–394, 2015. doi:10.1177/0278364914557736
- **J. A. DeCastro**, R. Ehlers, M. Rungger, A. Balkan, P. Tabuada, and H. Kress-Gazit. Dynamics-based reactive synthesis and automated revisions for high-level robot control. (submitted) *CoRR*, abs/1410.6375, 2014. arXiv:http://arxiv.org/abs/1410.6375.
- X. Zhang, L. Tang and **J. A. DeCastro**. Robust fault diagnosis of aircraft engines: a nonlinear adaptive estimation-based approach. *IEEE Trans. on Control Systems Technology*, 21(3):861–868, 2013. doi:10.1109/TCST.2012.2
- **J. A. DeCastro**. Rate-based model predictive control of turbofan engine clearance. *AIAA Journal of Propulsion and Power*. 23(4):804–813, 2007. doi:10.2514/1.25846

AIAA NOS Best Young Professional Paper

SELECTED
CONFERENCE
PUBLICATIONS

- **J. A. DeCastro**, J. Alonso-Mora, V. Raman, D. Rus and H. Kress-Gazit. Collision-free reactive mission and motion planning for multi-robot systems. To appear in: *Proceedings of the 17th International Symposium on Robotics Research (ISRR)*, Sestri Levante, Italy, September 12–15, 2015.
- **J. A. DeCastro**, V. Raman and H. Kress-Gazit. Dynamics-driven adaptive abstraction for reactive high-level mission and motion planning. In: *Proceedings of the IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA 2015)*, Seattle, WA, USA, May 26–30, 2015.
- **J. A. DeCastro** and H. Kress-Gazit. Guaranteeing reactive high-level behaviors for robots with complex dynamics. In: *Proceedings of the IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2013)*, Tokyo, Japan, November 3–8, 2013.
- **J. A. DeCastro**, L. Tang, B. Zhang and G. Vachtsevanos. A safety verification approach to fault-tolerant aircraft supervisory control. In: *Proceedings of the AIAA Guidance, Navigation, and Control Conference*, Portland, OR, USA, August 8–11, 2011.
- **J. A. DeCastro**, L. Tang, C. S. Byington and D. E. Culley. Analysis of fault-tolerance and decentralization concepts for distributed engine control. In: *Proceedings of the 45th AIAA Joint Propulsion Conference & Exhibit*, Denver, CO, USA, August 2–5, 2009.

ASME Propulsion Best Paper

J. A. DeCastro, J. S. Litt, and D. K. Frederick. A modular aero-propulsion system simulation of a large commercial aircraft engine. In: *Proceedings of the 44th AIAA/ASME/SAE/ASEE Joint Propulsion Conference & Exhibit*, Hartford, CT USA, July 21–23, 2008.

WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS **J. A. DeCastro**. Mission possible: guaranteeing reactive missions for complex robots. In: *ICRA 2015 Ph.D. Forum*, Seattle, WA, USA, May 26, 2015.

PUBLICATION AND	IEEE Conf. on Event-Based Control, Communication, and Signal Processing (EBCCSP)	2015
PAPER REVIEWING	International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	2014, 2015
EXPERIENCE	American Control Conference (ACC)	2014
	IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics	2011, 2012, 2013
	ASME Turbo Expo	2005, 2007, 2010
HONORS AND	Travel Grant to ICRA in Seattle, WA; sponsored by IEEE RAS and NSF	2015
AWARDS	Cornell MAE Fellowship, a merit-based award to incoming Ph.D. students	2011-2012
	ASME Propulsion Best Paper Award	2009
	NASA Group Achievement Award for outstanding group accomplishment (C-MAPSS Tea	im) 2009
	NASA Space Act Award for an outstanding technical contribution	2007
	AIAA Best Young Professional Paper awarded by the Northern Ohio Section of AIAA	2007